<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<target><person><fname>First and</fname><lname>Last Name</lname></person><emailaddress>Your_Email_Address@company.com</emailaddress><company>Your Company Name</company><salesperson>RenderX Sales</salesperson><salesemail>sales@renderx.com</salesemail>
<subject>RE: RenderX: Dynamic and Interactive PDF Forms Example</subject>
<body>
    
Thank you for testing RenderX's Dynamic and Interactive PDF Forms functionality with the new XEP 4.16 release.

Save the attachment to your desktop and open with WordPad or Text Editor to view the content.

Use Cases for "Dynamic and Interactive PDF Forms" by RenderX:

- A Power/Electricity Utility company. They wanted to "Go Green" as possible and save money in the process. They implemented e-mail PDF of Utility Bills and online access through the users account where the bill is generated dynamically. The "bill" is actually a PDF Form that allows the customer to submit their meter reading back to the utility company. Through the process, they have cut back on reading meters, choosing to see how the customer's responses will be. 

- A Cable Television company that send e-bills that are actually PDF Forms with targeted advertising (TransPromo). Clicking the PDF Form, submitting some information and voila, you have one-month free access to a movie channel. The PDF Form submittal is direct to the Utility companies server application that creates a transaction to their business system. The PDF Form contains all the hidden elements and information that identifies the user's account and since they are also the internet provider, they can even confirm against the IP address of the submitter.

- A Telephone company is using online statement presentment and bill pay directly from the PDF bill that is a form. A user can login in, get the e-bill, pay it by entering credit card information, and get a copy of the bill as a receipt -- all from the PDF Form transaction to a secure server.

- Sales and Marketing Campaign. A RenderX Partner has deployed PDF Forms to allow internal users to create and send custom letter campaigns. They generate a PDF Form with some fields that allow Sales and Marketing staff to input the information they want in the letter itself ... some verbiage for the particular campaign. The PDF Form is submitted and is transformed into the XSL that is applied to their marketing database to generate 100,000 letters for print and electronic delivery.


Do you have use cases / ideas to share with us? We look forward to hearing from you...


Regards,

RenderX, Inc.

Got XML? Need PDF Forms?
Get RenderX!
The Leader in XML to Print Technology

+1 (650) 327-1000  Sales
+1 (650) 328-8008 Fax
sales@renderx.com  
http://www.renderx.com

XEP 4.16 News Release at http://www.renderx.com/news/index.html#July_7,_2009

</body>
</target>
